Guide to the Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee records, 1957-2011 UA.01.08.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee records
1957-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee
UA.01.08.0003
3.5 Linear Feet
The Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee (formerly known as the Fritz London Memorial Award Committee) awards a monetary prize to outstanding scientists in the field of low-temperature physics. The prize was established in memory of Duke University physicist Fritz London. The collection contains correspondence, by-laws, conference listings, lists of prize nominees and awardees and other papers of committee members relating to the establishment of the award and the selection of the winners. Material in the collection ranges in date from 1957-2011.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Provenance
The Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1981-2011.
Historical Note
The Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee (formerly known as the Fritz London Memorial Award Committee) awards a monetary prize to outstanding scientists in the field of low-temperature physics. The prize was established in memory of Duke University physicist Fritz London. It was conceived in 1956 and first presented in 1957. Funds for the prize are derived from the Fritz London Endowment Fund, which is held in trust by Duke University. The committee is composed of four members plus a chairman, and the usual term of service is six years. In addition, the chairman of the Very Low Temperature (VLT) commission of the International Union of Pure and Applied Physics or an alternate designated by him (normally another member of the VLT commission) shall serve as an adjunct member to provide a link between the committee and the international low temperature physics committee. The award is bestowed every 2-3 years. Each committee is designated by number.
Collection Overview
The collection contains correspondence, by-laws, conference listings, lists of prize nominees and awardees and other papers of committee members relating to the establishment of the award and the selection of the winners. Material in the collection ranges in date from 1957-2011.
Related Material
Fritz London papers, 1922-1994 (bulk 1926-1954).
University Archives. Duke University.
Dept. of Physics records, 1946-1959.
University Archives. Duke University.
Science -- Awards; Low temperatures; Physics; Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee; International Union of Pure and Applied Physics; London, Fritz, 1900-1954
- Container List, 2 boxes
  - Correspondence, history of establishment of Award, 1957-1978 (Box 1)
  - 3rd Fritz London Award and some material on 4th, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Fritz London Award, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Nominations for 6th award, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Fritz London Award (Box 1)
  - Untitled file (includes correspondence, curriculum vitæ, and public relations material), 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Solicitation for 7th Fritz London Award, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Prof. John C. Wheatley, 1970 (Box 1)
  - 7th Award, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Ninth Fritz London Award Committee, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
  - 10th London Award Committee
    - Archives, includes list of winners, 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Membership, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Duke, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 15th Low Temperature Physics Congress, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Simon Prize, 1970, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Publicity, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Committee Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - General administrative, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - 10th Fritz London Award, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Endowment, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - London Prize Committee (Box 1)
  - London Prize Committee, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - 10th London Award nominations (Box 1)
  - London Prize nominations (Box 1)
  - London Prize, 1984 (Box 1)
  - 1978-1985 (Box 1)
  - London Award nominations (Box 1)
  - Certificates, 1970 (Box 1)
  - 12th, 13th Fritz London Award Committee (Box 1)
  - 13th Fritz London Award Committee (folders 1-2) (Box 1)
  - 13th Fritz London Award Committee (folders 3-5) (Box 2)
  - 14th Fritz London Award Committee, correspondence, 1990 (Box 2)
  - 14th Fritz London Award Committee, nominations, (4 folders), 1990 (Box 2)
  - 14th Fritz London Award Committee, other, 1990 (Box 2)
  - 15th Fritz London Award Committee (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 16th Fritz London Award Committee, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee, 1999 -- Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee, 1999 -- Nominations and Awardees (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee, 2002 (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee, 2005-- By-laws (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee, 2005 -- Nomination and Awardees (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee,2007-- Nomination Book 1 (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee,2007-- Nomination Book 2 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Fritz London Memorial Prize Committee, 2008 -- Committee Deliberations and Votes, 2007-2008 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 2011 Prize Nominations Info (5 Folders) (Box 3)
- Accession UA2014-0075: Horst Meyer Papers, 1987-2011
  - London Prize: its future? Correspondence, 2006 (Box 4)
  - LT 26-2011 London Prize, 2010-2011 (Box 4)
  - LT 25-2008 London Prize (Box 4)
  - London Prize, 2005 (Box 4)
  - London Prize, 2002 (Box 4)
  - London Award, 1999 (Box 4)
  - London Award, 1996 (Box 4)
  - London Award, 1993 (Box 4)
  - London Award, 1990 (Box 4)
  - London Award, 1987 (Box 4)
  - London Prize before 1987 (Box 4)